hello thanks for all joining it's active
textbook group
cohort one meeting 22
chapter 9 on October 28th
okay
we're in the seconds
discussion on chapter nine
model based data analysis
wouldn't like to
add anything they want
or mention how
the generative model discussion from
the previous
one hour
relates to model based data analysis
how does chapter four relate to chapter
nine
what does chapter nine
address
went to chapters 6 and 9 address that
chapter 4 doesn't
um I mean six is about thinking about
applying it
and uh like incredibly kind of
simplified
step-by-step kind of way
and 9 is very specifically about
answering scientific questions with it
and doing that uh with a sort of
this metabasian
it's like an almost nested
sort of schema of active immigrants
so I mean that's
the through line
I guess but
um
I'm not sure more than that you have to
say
that's really you know insightful thank
you Ali
uh yeah uh actually I would compare it
to a kind of learning how to
uh solve problems uh in I don't know
mathematics or I don't know uh physics
or other areas for example in
chapter 4
we we
acquired some necessary knowledge uh or
prerequisite about how to uh how to
think about uh the the phenomena or the
problem we're dealing with chapter six
kind of outlines a road map uh a roadmap
about
um how exactly we should proceed to
solve that problem in a kind of
formulaic way
and chapter nine uh actually uh in
chapter nine we get our hands dirty and
try to solve some of the actual or
empirical problems with the tools or
techniques we learned in chapter four
and six so in this um case I somehow
think of chapter 9 as a kind of uh case
study
well kind of cases studies or a kind of
solved problem section of uh this
textbook and uh yeah
I don't know how much
that captures their nature
that's great wow great thoughts I I
totally agree
let's look at the table of contents
chapter one special
overview chapter
mirror symmetry same but different with
10.
so now in the middle eight chapters
two chapters
on the low road and the high road
helping to two different approaches
which can be developed like
in a lot more detail
to approach active inference
from two fascinating and
non-controversial starting points
Bayesian inference from the low road
free energy principle
and the repeated measurement persistence
imperative
chapter four
is the first chapter on active inference
active inference is about the generative
models that are being specified
and how they're being computed
after just one chapter on active
inference
it goes to the area where the most
research and modeling has been done in
active inference
which is computational manalien
neuroanatomy
one chapter on active one chapter on the
primary domain
first half of the book
second half of the book
this is
the part where you're going to be
in parallel
perhaps on your first but perhaps not on
your first reading
you're going to be doing
playing through these
applied aspects of modeling
first is the recipe for Designing active
inference models
in chapter six as both of you
have um very nicely
set
then
the
figure 4.3 dialectic
discrete continuous time
is Revisited in two chapters
because
it probably
it's one key difference it's a minimum
of two
so it prevents like any like oh well it
has to be a pmdp it's like well
obviously not
so it keeps the space of generative
modeling open
and it allows for a discussion of the
very interesting topic of
hybrid active inference nested models
with continuous actuators for example
but discrete decision-making apparatus
so it just is like wanting to cover
these two key types of models in a bit
more detail than was addressed in
chapter four
but this was the first possible moment
to address it after
4.3 just kidding maybe about
then chapter nine or
yeah where we are now which is just okay
you've built your just pure discrete
time pure continuous time or hybrid
generative model
if it's a toy model you can just
generate data and just do whatever you
want
or
you might have
data from sensors or real world or
however
that's in the data format that your
generative model expected to receive
which was part of your design process
you could have determined what structure
literally the data is going to be in
is it going to be like yes data can be
reshaped but just broadly
is it like
256 sensors in a row of one or is it
like eight by eight
just those kinds of questions
so that when the data start coming in
for the experiment
whether you generated the data from the
generation generative model
or whether you're using it in a purely
recognition model capacity
on real world data
um
what does it look like to do statistical
modeling
with these statistical models that we've
been using
and then chapter 10 is a review
it restates what each chapter does
provide some further thoughts
and just summarizes
the unifying capacity
of active inference modeling
then they're the appendices
Ali
and also one uh in my opinion a very
interesting section of chapter nine is
uh the section on
models of false inference section 9.7 in
which there's an interesting
definition of the disorders
I mean the mental disorders and how we
can actually
computationally model those uh different
disorders
sorry it says that
here the the disorder does not
necessarily imply that the inferential
mechanism is flawed in most of the
studies the inferential mechanism
operates normally but based on a flawed
generative model so that's basically
what we had learned about how we can
somehow update our beliefs or correct
their perceptions based on either
refining our generative model or
modifying our generative model or
um somehow sometimes we can just well
act upon those errors and try to reduce
our uncertainties but in this case uh
it's a very interesting point and uh
the case of computational pathologies
because
oftentimes people ask well what does
active inference actually explain
so I think this is a very good example
of it's a very meaningful and
significant application uh I mean in any
sense of the word so if we can uh
somehow computationally
model these kind of disorders uh will
most probably have a much better
understanding of its origin
and the way to
probable
treatments of those disorders and many
other applications uh can come to uh
comes to mind but yeah I think this part
of the chapter 9 is something that was
not addressed quite explicitly in the
previous chapters and I in my opinion is
the most interesting part of this one
great awesome yeah it reminds me of the
table in chapter four
of chapter five with the
neurotransmitters
so that was they were still at the
Oregon systems level in chapter five
but five is very much related to nine I
guess in that sense as well
because it's like it's like here's what
dopamine does here's what acetylcholine
does just
at the computational model level
and then here it's like
that computational model was fit like
between
the phenomena
like attention or policy Precision
however
phenomena to a molecule
in chapter five
here
the phenomena is being connected to a
real human clinical application
so it's not that we're saying
or anyone is saying or you know anything
like that that the molecule is being
pure directly linked
to
this paper even if it's mentioned
the direct linkage approach is
people in group X have more molecule
have less molecule
and even the neural Imaging approach
can be seen as a variant of that which
is people in group X have more brain
activation pattern
in computational pathology
those kinds of biochemical measurements
and neuroimaging measurements can and
they are used
however
this type of computational modeling
is referring to
parametric modeling
where the parameters
are related to the Pathology
so it's not an a priori classification
of those with and without
and then descriptive statistics showing
that a biochemical or a brain Imaging
pattern are differentially expressed
that's descriptive statistics
it's not computational pathology it
might be precision
pathology
but it could still be Precision or big
data or however with just like purely
doing data summaries doing a random
forest model to diagnose
these models have a cognitive
structural hypothesis about the nature
of these phenomena
like the ocular motor syndromes again
it's not just people with the diagnosis
and without it's a neurocognitive model
of eye Behavior
and then
explanations can be made
from clinical data
by rendering various aspects of the
generative model conditionally
independent of others ocular motor
syndromes such as intranuclear
optimalges
may be induced
so if you just were diagnosing these as
different conditions maybe they have
similar etiologies
how the condition arises maybe they have
different maybe they have multiple
but these two conditions
computationally can be understood as
parametric modulating
in a computational model of ocular motor
Behavior
this isn't people with internuclear
opto-date
have higher glucose
or lower glucose or this brain region or
this
aspect of them
those are all absolutely valid
approaches
that's like scientific methodological
pluralism
which is like it's okay that people want
to do different approaches everybody's
contributing
to a common
people who care about this and are
creating high quality reproducible data
their data will always be useful
and their perspectives are valid and we
don't want to have
um a discourse space on inter-nuclear
optimal Malaysia
that's
um
you know
like uh saying that one model is like
simply
the only correct model
this paper makes a positive contribution
and points to some new
ways of thinking about
various
pathologies
and Thinking Beyond the ways that
they've been
worked on before
one can imagine that before 2000 and so
on you had what health records
and you have some double-blind
experiments
and so you might do a meta-analysis to
find correlations with features of
people and all of those things that
we've been describing
but it was not plausible
to actually implement
computational models of these phenomena
now interestingly that's something that
can be worked on by researchers
directly
and then somebody can a a doctor could
download
ocularmotor syndromes Dot
programming
dot you know
whatever it is but this can be developed
in a pure research context
and the generative model is like the
interface
for the kind of information
[Music]
that might not be available to the
person developing the generative model
because it relates to a lot of problems
and issues about data
availability
that's one's kind of just side note
but that's all but really thanks for
raising that point and then I just
wanted to emphasize
and unpack
which is that these this table which is
taking up two and a half pages of a
pretty short book
is describing
these are like the cases that can be
brought up which they're providing in a
helpful table
for what active inference describes
so if the principle of least action
gauge Theory Etc
sophistication does not interest one
these are more pragmatic value
now that will probably move the goal
post to
show me where the computational modeling
helped somebody with delusions
and that's a Fine Place to want to go
but it's also a standard and an approach
that
it's not related to the substance of the
theoretical development
I mean I think you could probably
do the response to that question might
be something like
the difficulty of
implementing that model in a way that
provides
you know actionable
real-time
you know affordances to address
the aberrant priors in a way that's
causally you know going it's going to
actually affect that uh system is
we need
you know either more compute or a
particular kind of algorithmic medicine
that doesn't exist yet or Etc like but
that's not
a problem with the particular approach
it's just an insufficiency of
ability to enact it I guess
um
but I wanted to ask a question
about specifically this uh
aberrant prior beliefs it says
ultimately the pathology is a
consequence of average height beliefs
it's not the generative model advert
product boost is that
um
I think I think this is like I'll use
point is and everything that you just
went through is correct that this is
kind of where the rubber really meets
the road for
its value and demonstrating or whatever
um but
um
I'm wondering also
to me that there's like a easy confusion
thing there about beliefs and priors and
so
um well if they just believed the right
thing
then they wouldn't have these you know
um so that's not that's not really what
that means though right so uh like is
another way of saying this like in the
Oculus motor
uh
you know disorder case like a you know
kind of uh
neurobiological like you know bias in in
some kinds of cells or whatever right
for that's like
you know pathologically different than
normal or whatever like
some you know receptor for a particular
chemical or whatever is that
a kind of thing that the way of saying
that differently that you know that
particular case that is
more commensurate with what they're
actually saying there
or like you know more commensurate but
just
not relying on
jargon and or
domain knowledge specific for what I
mean by beliefs and prayers is that
or is that not right
yeah well there's a lot
there are you talking about the
comparison of the terms beliefs and
prayers
in relationship to the way people might
naturally interpret such
beliefs to be and they may indeed be
people's beliefs about the world in the
conversational sense
like some beliefs are just your retinal
States
but other states of the world as if or
really
are your States on other things
right
um yeah I mean I'm I guess I'm asking if
beliefs is
um
but in some cases it is beliefs but uh
it's also another way of stating
if another way of stating that is like a
like physical like a structural
like systemic bias for one thing or
another or whatever you know in that
context is that um
you know the like physical or
informational kind of
non
-folk psychology
does that commensurate with what they
mean by beliefs there
okay let's try that yeah Ali please
first
sorry uh I'm sorry but you mean uh the
um statistical use of the word uh belief
because
um in statistics and in folk psychology
uh as far as I know this term is used in
quite different ways yeah so uh I guess
that which what you're talking about is
uh these statistical sense of the word
belief and if it maps onto the folk
psychological uh sense of this term or
uh am I missing something here
um well let's just take two steps back
for a second and just in the text it
says
um
at the bottom of page
185 here that at the top of that yeah uh
it says
um
the infertile uh mechanism operates
normally but based uh on a flawed
generative model this means that
ultimately pathology is a consequence of
aberrant prior beliefs
yeah and I'm and I'm asking
um a kind of just
explicate different whatever uh
right there in in the context of
psychological disorders which is not
necessarily pathology but I'm just you
know if you tell somebody oh yeah it
helps with uh it was the the impetus or
whatever for this whole thing was
to think about
um
yeah like specifically like
schizophrenia and other you know but
that's
immediately
kind of puts it in that category or that
context of definitions and so uh just uh
kind of
you know Nuance the term their beliefs a
little bit
um
yeah
is it commensurate with the rest of the
text
uh to say like in the case of this you
know like specifically of uh this uh
oculine motor uh disorder category
like you're saying beliefs in the retina
or something like that that is
um like cones like being sensitive to
something they they well it's just what
they are sensitive to and in this
particular person
you know they're just sensitive to or
whatever the relevant you know structure
is there but it's you know sensitive to
to something right and that's its belief
you know in some sense
um
what's the statistical definition or
anything like that but just is a
is that completely off track or is that
I have a thought but Ali if you want to
make a response please
uh yeah uh I think that this term
believe and it's uh different meanings
in different contexts uh actually uh
sort of bleed into each other and uh
there cannot possibly be uh separated uh
cleanly from uh from each other so
um in this particular case I believe
that the word belief
uh in the is part and partly is um
this folk psychological uh sense of the
word and uh partly it's based on the uh
kind of philosophical slash
epistemological uh sense of this word
because uh especially in epistemology uh
when uh philosophers talk about belief
usually they don't mean just the folk
psychological sense of this term
although it relates to that concept but
it's much more nuanced than that so uh
in the case of ocular motor pathology
well I believe that the word belief
somehow can be interpreted in a little
more abstract philosophical sense or
epistemological sense of this word than
our
both psychological sense of it so uh but
again
I think it also has some overlappings
with uh the folks psychological sense of
it as well
great thought
just to kind of reset that then say what
I was planning to before so here it's
situational
um where people talk commonly about uh
don't talk about beliefs like the I like
where it believes it should be looking
[Music]
um
people don't talk about that but there
might be another cognitive model that
does align very well within expressed
felt cognitive belief
and everything in between
and bundles that are mixed
like people who believe that they're
accurate on a task but actually are low
accuracy
so it's going to be very model specific
I think how it Maps the different
people's understanding but what I was uh
is that was what Ali's response kind of
made me
think about and that's why I didn't
choose an example like delusions
to focus on
because that is related to the felt or
experienced
or reported
phenomena
um Okay so
beliefs and prayers and this question of
disorders of inference which as Brock
mentioned was like part of the early
impetus
in relating to studying for example
schizophrenia and
fristin's earlier
and continued work
maybe there's a part I'm missing and
maybe it's not the right context or way
but
um I think
first we can narrowly interpret what
they use to mean disorder and then have
a more broad perspective so
I read this does not necessarily imply
the inferential mechanisms flawed like
the CPU has the right number of Cycles
the Machinery are not flawed the car is
operating at normal burning temperature
given its generative model as specified
chapter four
it is doing appropriate variational
message passing belief propagation
approximate Bayesian computation
Bayesian brain however you want to see
it
given what this person has experienced
and their parameterization
it's not the case that they're making a
fallacious estimate
now that's sort of in the situations
where it's like yeah okay but you're
going to say that for whatever they do
do
but it's like that's kind of that
tautology it's like right that's our
best estimate of the system as it is
just how it is
in most of the studies reviewed in table
9.1 which is to say
the pathologies that are identified in
table 9.1
the inferential mechanism operates
normally as per the previous meaning but
based upon a flaw generative model
and it's literally like there's the rub
aberrant prior beliefs is like what and
so that is where I would say
there's two ways to zoom out from that
and contextualize that statement the
first is aberrant prior beliefs are not
intrinsically operant
whether they're
um subconsciously or consciously held I
believe in itself is not operant
but there's the niche
and especially just the human cultural
when we're talking about these felt
beliefs
so in the niche it's like there is ant
colonies that were high foraging and low
foraging
those are not aberrances of foraging
Behavior that's variation in foraging
Behavior with respect to variation in
weather
and there was probably decades where one
was better than the other
and that's why there's evolution
so it's like
what's the per okay so level one of
aberrant is in a niche context
and then especially for these like
expressively
human
um experienced
settings
that's where I think there's an
opportunity again not saying that this
paragraph is the right place in this
textbook
but that's where it's important to also
bring in like the um like
I'm not expert in this area but like
Foucault social descriptions of um
mental illness diagnosis
well they're only crazy if the majority
of people and something
this book yeah which I've mentioned on
live streams before if I could just
describe why I bring it up and like how
I think it's relevant to chapter nine
is just like
she's saying there's different methods
and there's different theoretical
interpretations
and it's very clear
and it's very
pluralist and though guided
everybody will also I think see like
deeper aspects too but just I studied
with Helen
in Stanford
and she it was just very like
it's very interesting to
see that coming from philosophy
because in the scientific domains it's
like not framed that way
it's like we could have a generative
model for these
conditions and scenarios
that integrates different types of
information
in a situational way with a sparse model
and we could all work on that and then
different people could have different
data sets or different public or private
data sets
but that requires not just sort of like
operational coordination
and ontology driven design and other
features
but it also requires a
basically personally held commitment to
pluralism
at least in practice
because there's too many methods and
methods are too
Last Mile
to
dictate
models of phenomena
these are not measurements
but they're generated alongside and with
and from measurements
and so that's not descriptive statistics
per se
and that's a major difference in this
what you can do with the Tail of Two
densities
approaches these situations differently
than one might see in a
Health Journal
showing
the population level factors associated
with a disease
this is a different kind of study
but it could be done in a population
context
which has been done extensively in SPM
and neuroimaging
so you can still bring in features of
the people
and understand how different features of
people are quite literally associated
with the diagnosis
and
that is seen as a label
on a neurocognitive Model A generative
model
now what's the generative model
chapter 4 chapter 6.
and then it's like okay we're just going
to say that all of the people's ocular
motor circuitry
are structurally the same
and we're going to explore how the two
groups differ in the parameter estimates
of these different features
or you could say I'm studying a
situation where this region has been
severed
so the hypothesis I'm testing is
actually whether this connectivity
versus this connectivity is going to
have this observable difference
that's testing a structural hypothesis
so you could test parametric hypotheses
within a generative model
and or structural hypotheses across but
to kind of returns at this point
those are these two ways that the model
can be quote in in their you know way
aberrant or flawed
quite literally
it could be a parametric
estimate that's aberrant
which as discussed does not mean
intrinsically bad number 4.2 or 37.3 is
not bad it's about its relationship
within a niche in a fitness context and
like all of that
so it could be a parametric
uh aberrance
with respect to a state estimator like
an expectation on a variable variable or
precision
so that's the LaPlace approximation
it's the hierarchical predictive proc
processing approximation
slash structure expectation variance
mean variance mode variance
center of the path
width of the path
those are the two gaussian
distribution takes two parameters
LaPlace approximation takes two
parameters
hierarchical message uh passing
has these kinds of
variables
or
it can be structural differences
which is quite open-ended
how is this useful
an example is provided
here
potentially for example let's just say
that there's people who do and do do not
have a certain situation
um some moths go towards the light and
some don't
is that because of differences in their
behavior
where the statistical variance
gets loaded onto differences in
their realized preference vector
or their habit
e
so it there could be a behavioral setup
that would do you know the Fibonacci
pattern of variability just whatever it
happened to be which is extensively
described in SPM how to time different
behavioral stimuli
some natural observational setting or
controlled behavioral setting both of
which have pros and cons
both quote controlled conditions in the
lab and natural observation they have
pros and cons
but the idea in model-based analysis is
that those can be the observables
and you may or may not control the
observations but at least you know what
they are
and then you can explore whether
differences in Behavior
end up being reflected
in statistically differentiable
parameter estimates
for
prior preference or for prior D or for
the fixed form term e
okay
Ollie
uh and yes for what it's worth I also
put a code from uh this recent paper by
Carl Preston from a couple of months ago
which is by the way is a great uh
overview of this whole field of
computation Psychiatry through the lens
of active imprints and here
it provides
a clear and explicit definition of the
term belief used in this area so
I thought
like that might be helpful here
the kind of belief beliefs here are
Bayesian beliefs and then it goes on to
describe what Bayesian beliefs mean
awesome
um
cool that is super clarifying
I think
um
it makes a lot of sense
and I I so I have uh still a kind of
maybe
I don't know if
the answer
was already given exactly or I'll just
ask it a different slightly different
way about
um
the the separation between the
generative model and the priors here
in
this toy you know frog jumping example
are
are the aberrant priors the you know the
Frog Apple Distribution on that belief
beforehand
and
the observation the updating all of that
being the general model is working as
you know intended but it's just that
the
priors were so out of whack
that when you know the
generative model kind of observes and
steps through or whatever that it's um
you know uh it just ends up in the wrong
State and or is is the likelihood model
it just I'm not sure I guess in this in
the toy example there how you could have
how it would be I guess the the parts
that's missing there is the context
maybe but um
yeah like if I had a prior belief that
was different than your prior belief but
we weren't you know we didn't have a
disorder or whatever I would imagine our
priors wouldn't be the same but they
would still kind of converge
um
so I'm not sure how you get there
without uh
an outside prior belief or something
about the environment that's totally
wrong right or like or
you know some something else about the
environment or the likelihood model is
somehow really wrong
yeah thanks great question those are
exactly the two greetings welcome back
Ellie those are exactly like the two let
me unpack that in the pathology example
so Society expects us and or
we actually die or have consequences
with when the Frog when it's a frog
you're not supposed to eat it apples are
okay to eat
now if you uh turn down too many apples
you starve
if you eat too many frogs you die
so you have to balance your type 1 and
type 2 false positive and false negative
error rates
in this eat do not eat
jump does not jump observation setting
because these aren't just these are idle
classifiers here but we can imagine
these as more action-oriented
classifiers
apples are for eating frogs are for
throwing
um
now society and or the niche defines
aberrant Behavior
as one that does not conform
to expectations or
to the to the um
to a thriving state in the niche
while recognizing that all parameter
values that are actually observed are at
least there
now that doesn't mean you want them to
be there they want them but also then
that's a belief an agent has about
another system that also exists
so there would be many ways
to see that aberrant Behavior
so if you um like speaking to the person
who discards too many apples
maybe they believe that they have a
strong prior on frogs
0.5
or their likelihood which which is also
a parametric belief
is different
they have a different action mapping now
here's the question now you put them in
the lab and you have jumping and
non-jumping frogs and apples
and then you can use those experimental
techniques
to
on a computational model
narrowly to determine do they simply
expect
frogs to appear
but they know what frogs and apples do
or
do they have
an appropriate belief about the
likelihood a priori of frogs and apples
but they have an incorrect action
mapping
I hope I said it correctly but I think
you get the picture the point is you
could then use experiments
to determine whether groups of people
who had effective or ineffective
Behavior
and then if somebody for example
had an overestimate of frogs
then the message to pass is frogs are
not as common as you think
whereas if there was somebody with a
variance interpretable variance
here in the likelihood model difference
with some other preference again keeping
your mind that that's still like it's
like outlier detection and
attracting
which isn't even necessarily A
preferable thing
but just pointing out just statistically
this person's
model would be updated by saying
you know it's not known that apples can
jump but actually they can't
it's possible that apples jump so next
time something jumps don't just throw it
away
and those are very different
points to convey
and this is a very simple example
but it's helpful to think about because
those are the kinds of parameters if
this was your model of of um
schizophrenia those would be your levers
or your knobs if you had a more complex
model and the models are more complex
then there's a lot more Associated
um you know
challenge Yacht Rock
oh no I was just going to say that you
know yeah that was really helpful and um
I don't even know
it seems
I mean obviously I don't I know next to
nothing I guess about Psychiatry uh
I don't know how you do it though
without something like this I mean
I guess
they were doing something kind of like
this approximately like informally
to some degree in some cases but like I
don't like it would seem like just
guessing almost
and
well I don't know yeah well I I even for
about
schizophrenia without something like
this so
well to simplify a complex area
there was studies that Associated either
a biomolecule or a genetic variant but
especially biomolecules and brain
Imaging
directly to a diagnosis which from a
health records perspective exactly makes
sense it's the data you have however
this is a um
unobserved model
of the phenomena itself
that can incorporate measurements
including health records
and that allows the development of an
actual understanding of the etiology and
the causation
and therefore could be used to justify
traditionally understood interventions
or suggest different
Behavior
and interventions like maybe you don't
just oh you're low on this just take
this thing that raises it it's like
maybe that's not exactly the move
but there's more precise like affordance
to do that yeah yeah including the
counterfactuals like in a clinical
setting that is going to be quite
interesting all right let's just in the
last minutes
look to 10.
Minsky
active inference as a unified theory of
sentient Behavior
if anybody wants to do a little like
Twitter thread recap on the sentient
the sentience discourse over the last
few weeks I'm sure we can find some
funny tweets but with the sentient pong
playing neurons
and just wave after wave of
semantic discussion about the term
sentience
in this chapter we wrap up active
inference main theoretical points from
the first part of the book chapter one
through five and its practical
implementations from the second part six
through ten then we connect the dots
we abstract away from the specific
active inference models discussed in
previous chapters to focus on
integrative aspects of the framework
benefits of active
summary of the book 10.2 chapter 1
chapter 2. chapter 3 chapter 4.
5 6.
7 and 8.
No Love
chapter nine you just read it
go read it again
um
connecting the dots the integrative
perspective on active imprints
interestingly framed in terms of some
early
Dennett work
a call to model the whole iguana a
complete cognitive creature perhaps a
simple one and an environmental Niche
for it to cope with
rather than
single dimensional
analyzes and measurements on a complex
system
just too much like a whirlwind
to just measure and oh well brain
regions correlated with this and this
region is correlated with that
those kinds of structural and um
behavioral morphological any given
measurement
does not ever get at
the underlying causal structure
unless you specifically model it that
way
active inference helps with that issue
by offering a first principle account of
the ways in which organisms solve their
adaptive problems
so by Framing attention memory
anticipation
under common
computational
framings
and a unified imperative
it's possible to integrate different
kinds of phenomena
memory
attention
can be thought of as optimizing same
objective
10-4 predictive brains predictive minds
and predictive processing
kind of a provocative
selection
active inference creatures or their
brains are probabilistic inference
machines
connecting to the kind of
focus of predictive mind predictive
brain predictive processing coding
area
which is like
the real time and anticipatory
especially
real-time unfolding anticipation
self-evidencing prediction
predictive processing specifically
livestream 43.
perception
section 10.5
helmholtz
perception is unconscious inference
then how that was implemented in
Bayesian brain Bayesian brain
the inactive turn the pragmatic turn
action control
bringing action in
end of live stream 43 end of paper 43.
idea motor
cybernetic some other ontologies that
are kind of like
easily functionally
equated with parts of active idea motor
theories cybernetics optimal control
theory utility decision making Bayesian
decision
rate reinforcement learning
planning as inference behavior and
bounded rationality
and then specifically what free energy
brings into pounded rationality valence
emotion of motivation
homeostasis allostasis and terosceptive
processing
attention salience epistemic Dynamics
rule learning causal inference fast
generalization
and next steps
social machine learning and Robotics
summary Lord of the Rings
we are confident that you will continue
to pursue active inference in some form
so it's a quite long chapter there's a
lot in it
we'll talk about it next time
thank you fellows
bye